<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons why the supreme authority of the three nations (for the time) is not in the Parliament, but in the new-established Councel of State, consisting of His Excellence the Lord General Cromvvel, and his honourable assessors. Written in answer to a letter sent from a gentleman in Scotland to a friend of his in London. To which is added the letter it self.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E697_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202945</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863068</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115250</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115250)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 107:E697[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons why the supreme authority of the three nations (for the time) is not in the Parliament, but in the new-established Councel of State, consisting of His Excellence the Lord General Cromvvel, and his honourable assessors. Written in answer to a letter sent from a gentleman in Scotland to a friend of his in London. To which is added the letter it self.</title>
                  <author>C. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>and are to be sold by Rich. Moone, at the seven Stars in Pauls Church-yard, neer the great north-door.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A printing of and reply to a letter signed "C.N.".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>C. N. --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Council of State --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115250:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS WHY THE Supreme Authority OF THE THREE NATIONS (For the time) Is not in the PARLIAMENT, BUT In the new-eſtabliſhed Councel of State, CONSISTING OF His Excellence the Lord General CROMVVEL, And his honourable Aſſeſſors.</p>
            <p>Written in anſwer to a Letter ſent from a Gentleman in <hi>Scotland</hi> to a friend of his in <hi>London.</hi> To which is added the Letter it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Rich. Moone,</hi> at the ſeven Stars in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, neer the great North-door. 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:115250:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115250:2"/>
            <head>The LETTER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His late diſſolution of the <hi>Parliament</hi> puts us all here in a maze, and the moſt of this Country conceive themſelves thereby to be in a worſe condition then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; both for that the little bloſſoming hopes, which the People here (eſpecially the Clergy) were beginning to entertaine of ſome favour from the Presbyterian party ſitting in the Houſe, are now quite blaſted and blown away: as likewiſe becauſe we apprehend (how juſtly I cannot tell) that the unexperiencedneſs, and illiteracie of military men in the diſquiſition of divine or legal concernments, will by all appearance bring us to ſubmit our necks to the abſolute, uncontroulable, and arbitrary yoak of the ſword: into which jealouſies we are the more forcibly driven, that we think that act, whereby a rupture was made into the ſacred authority of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to have been both raſh, unlawfull, and ſtrange: and that ſo much the more, that thoſe Parliamentary men were accounted the refuge and ſanctuary of the People, the Repreſentatives of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the braines of that politick body, whereof the <hi>Army</hi> is but the hands, and chuſers and preferrers of theſe very men to their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive places, that were the extruders of them. I pray you <hi>Sir</hi> let me have your opinion of this great and ſudden change by the next Poſt, whether you think the proceeding illegal or no, if conducible or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the good of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and how <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> ſtand affected to the now eſtabliſhed Councel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>This Tueſday <hi>May 10. 1653.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>C.N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115250:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> ANSWER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SOme other <hi>returnes</hi> from me to former <hi>Letters</hi> of yours upon ſubjects of the nature of that, which came to my hands this <hi>Munday</hi> the 16 of <hi>May,</hi> having as often as they were ſent received from you that acceptance, which, by ſpirits of your ingenuity, is uſually beſtowed on men of ſuch unprejudicate opinions, as, out of my affection to truth (without by-endes of my own) I have oftentimes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry freely laid before you: do now encourage me in anſwer to your laſt of the date of the 10 of <hi>May,</hi> by which you are pleaſed to demand my ſentiment concerning the new eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed authority, after the abrupt diſſolution of the late tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decennial <hi>Parliament,</hi> to give my pen as much ſcope, for your ſatisfaction, and the undeceiving of thoſe, that poſſibly are miſ-informed of my <hi>Lord General,</hi> &amp; his honorable Councel of <hi>Officers,</hi> as in the interval betwixt the time of <hi>Mundays</hi> coming packet, &amp; that of <hi>Tueſdays</hi> going one, I can get ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from my other too too urgent occaſions; Therefore do I expect of your courteſie, in caſe no more preſſing buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deprive me of leiſure, that you would be pleaſed to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the contingence of my excurſion beyond the ordinary limits of an <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> the prolixity will undoubtedly prove to you the leſs tedious, that you be thereby informed of the lawfulneſs of the change: of the Nations of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Irelands</hi> approbation of it: and of <hi>Scotlands</hi> greater apparent happineſs under it then the former Government; of all being mentioned in your <hi>Letter</hi>) I am obliged in anſwer thereto, to give you the beſt account I can.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115250:3"/>
            <p>Here do I intend to propound little or nothing of <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> although the moſt of the <hi>Parliamentary</hi> writers make that to be the main reaſon of turning the <hi>Monarchy</hi> of this Land unto a <hi>State;</hi> and that many others have ſaid that the preſervation of both the <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> did totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon this late reſolute action of breaking up the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> it ſhall ſuffice me, and I hope not diſpleaſe you, that I endeavour to juſtifie the deed by the mildeſt and moſt moderate arguments can be deviſed, and of a nature averſe from aſperſing (but as little as may be) any former Judicatory.</p>
            <p>Now if the queſtion be ſtated, whether the Supreme au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority be in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or the <hi>Army;</hi> and that for the eſtabliſhment thereof both power and lawfulneſs be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required, I doubt me all reaſon will carry it for the <hi>Army.</hi> Here would I intreat ſuch as are of another opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to make appear what it is they mean by the word <hi>Parliament,</hi> whether it be that kind of convention which the <hi>army</hi> did allow to ſit at <hi>Weſtm.</hi> or the preceding one, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> which (as the ſoul of man is ſaid to comprehend the <hi>rational, ſenſitive,</hi> and <hi>vegetative</hi> faculties) was firſt conſtituted <hi>triennial,</hi> and afterwards by vertue of the ſame <hi>Royal</hi> ſource, from whence the former grant did flow, prolonged or perpetuated at the pleaſure and diſcretion of the ſitters: I believe that thoſe who having declared againſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> do cordially decline it, will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther admit of the former acception of the word; though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it be ſaid, that the <hi>army</hi> derived its power from the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and not the <hi>Parliament</hi> from it; for I may ſay that the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> choſe the <hi>Army;</hi> which Army (when the <hi>Lords</hi> &amp; many of the <hi>Commons</hi> had, by preſſing too hard upon the Liberty of the ſubject, forfeited their places) took into their protection that part of the Houſe which voted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115250:4"/>down <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and was called the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> by which means I take it to be clear enough, that the Supremacy is in the <hi>Army,</hi> till they be pleaſed to reſigne it in the fovour of new <hi>Repreſentatives;</hi> for <hi>Parliaments</hi> were never hithereto called but by <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Queens</hi> of a <hi>regal</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and that to parley with them, and adviſe them in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult matters, ſo that the very word thereof ſeemeth to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of malignancy, and probably ought to have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as the terme of the lower Houſe was turned to that of the Houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi> Nevertheleſs paſſing by meer words, there being nothing more certain then that the thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the word <hi>Parliament</hi> was nothing elſe but the <hi>Kings</hi> great <hi>Councel,</hi> there being no more <hi>King,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> by infallible conſequence is a <hi>non-entitie;</hi> and therefore <hi>Monarchy</hi> being extinct, the government of the Nation is inherent for the time in the perſons of my <hi>Lord General,</hi> and his Councel of <hi>Officers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not the <hi>Nation</hi> or any one therein ſtartle at this, for as it is juſt where the power of <hi>Protection</hi> is, that there ſhould be the <hi>Authority</hi> (all of us owing <hi>obedience</hi> to thoſe that do <hi>protect</hi> us) ſo is it no new thing that ſo legal a right be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically exerced: is it not plainly ſet down in the <hi>Judges,</hi> how <hi>Ehud,</hi> after having killed King <hi>Eglon,</hi> ruled all <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the ſpace of many years? did not the Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large it ſelf farther under the command of the <hi>Souldiery</hi> then the <hi>Senate;</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth flouriſh more under <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> then ever it did either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after their times? and yet I may very warrantably avouch, that the preſent <hi>Lord General</hi> of <hi>England</hi> was never ſo much ſubordinate to this <hi>State,</hi> as both of them were to that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we look into the ſtate of Nature, which is that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>archies</hi> and <hi>States</hi> are poſited, both in relation to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115250:4"/>one another, and in the manner of their own eſtabliſhment, we ſhall very evidently perceive, that in whoſe perſon or perſons the power is devolved, there reſteth the <hi>Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Nor is it meer ſtrength that bringeth one or many to this power, it being requiſite that wiſdom and other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring qualifications contribute to ſo great a work: the Fox is wiſer then the Lion, yet is the Lion king of brutes; not but that there are beaſts ſtronger then he, (as is the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant) but that there is none in which ſtrength, wit, agility, and generoſity together are better commixed. My <hi>Lord General</hi> and the <hi>Officers</hi> of his <hi>Army</hi> are truly ſuch: hath any people or nation out-witted them in their Treaties? hath any been more expedite in the active part? more valiant in the field, more patient in hardſhips, or more noble and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful then they after an obtained victory? Did all theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments ever meet together in a <hi>Parliament,</hi> or concentre in a promiſcuous unmilitary Body of Country-Gentlemen and Lawyers? It was the <hi>Army,</hi> I believe, and not the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> by whoſe wit and valour <hi>Ireland</hi> was reduced, <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> pacified, and <hi>England</hi> eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>What though they be Sword-men, ſhould that derogate from their Authority? I ſay, No; for that God, who is Goodneſs in the abſtract, and Wiſdom it ſelf, although he be called neither God nor Lord of Learning or Law, is no more intituled the God of Peace then he is the Lord of Hoſts; the later title, by all appearance (if I may ſay ſo) being the more honourable, in that we worſhip God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is powerful, and love him for his goodneſs.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, there is hardly any Argument that the Lord brings in the <hi>Scripture</hi> for his being the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that is not deduced from his power, as the drowning of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi>'s Army in the Red ſea, the deſtroying of the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> the laying of the foundations of the earth, and ſetting of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115250:5"/>bounds to the Sea: nor were the new <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who are the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> otherwiſe convinced of the Divinity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then by Miracles, which were the extraordinary effects of his power.</p>
            <p>Thus do I conceive that the ſole power of the Land is in my <hi>Lord General</hi> and the <hi>Army,</hi> and that no <hi>State</hi> can be well governed, where Authority is divorced from Power; for without Power, Authority is but as a naked <hi>Virgin</hi> expoſed to the raging luſt of a <hi>Satyr;</hi> nor where theſe two are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from each other, can the Good be rewarded, or the Wicked corrected; becauſe a State, how peremptory and commanding ſoever it be in iſſuing out of Orders, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able without a conſiderable power to confer recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences and inflict puniſhments. And if you think, that by ſuch means we lie at the mercy of the Sword, being under the command of Military Officers; I muſt needs ask you, If you would rather be under Maſters that have no Swords, and ſo be expoſed to the devouring ſword of Forraigners?</p>
            <p>The Safety of the People is ſaid to be the Supreme Law, yet are thoſe that have the power in their hands the fitteſt Judges of that ſafety; becauſe they are the beſt able to conſider what and where the ſtrength is which is the Guard of the Nation: nor is there any reaſon why we ſhould be diffident of the diſcretion of thoſe Officers, who are men of Publike ſpirits, &amp; ſuch as have not ſought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs; and therefore deſerve to be accounted our Maſters, by defending us from the violence of others, and preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us in thoſe Rights that belong unto us.</p>
            <p>We were made ſubject to this late <hi>Parliament</hi> (if we may ſo call it) by the meer vertue of that power wherewith the <hi>Army</hi> did protect it: and thus, by ſaving of our lives and goods, they have juſtly gained more dominion over us, then others can claim right unto. And ſeeing <hi>Egypt</hi> for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115250:5"/>Ages together was well governed by the Souldier-<hi>Mamaluks,</hi> who were not a free-born people, Should this Iſland grudge to be ruled by the freeſt ſpirited men in the world, and that under the conduct of my Lord General <hi>Cromwel,</hi> which title of <hi>General</hi> (for his ſake) ought to be reputed no leſs honourable amongſt us, then that of <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator</hi> was amongſt the <hi>Romanes.</hi> And to mount yet a little higher, I muſt needs think, that the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> who is not aſhamed to take the name of <hi>Generaliſsimo</hi> upon him, would not have us to be ſo inconſiderate, as to diſreſpect the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a <hi>General;</hi> eſpecially for that being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be like our Father that is in heaven, that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of all other is without doubt moſt rational, which draweth neereſt to the model of His. God is our <hi>General,</hi> and did not onely hazard his life for our good, but died for us in the perſon of his Son. Let the <hi>Cherubims</hi> and <hi>Seraphins</hi> take the title of <hi>Parliament</hi> upon them, if they will, yet ſtill is the <hi>Lord of hoſts</hi> above them. For my own part, I would prefer the Sword of <hi>Gideon</hi> to the Rod of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> and the <hi>Laurel</hi> to the <hi>Long Robe.</hi> Is not the High-Conſtable of <hi>France</hi> above the Chancellor, and a Knight in the Field before a Doctor in the Law? So ſhould the General of our Army be above any Member in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and the Officers he adjoyneth to him partake of his pre-eminence.</p>
            <p>Whereas you ſay, that thoſe Military men are not like to be ſuch Politicians, in foreſeeing the dangers may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal the Country, as the Members of Parliament; I anſwer, If that Policie conſiſt in preſerving us from the Invaſion of ſtrangers, and diſcovery of Plots amongſt our ſelves at home, That no men can be thought fitter then thoſe that are in hazard daily, by the prevention or withſtanding of thoſe inconveniences. Do not Apprentiſhips make Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115250:6"/>ſo perfect in their Callings, that the moſt ingenious Scholar, how pregnant ſoever he be in ſetting down the myſteries of a Trade, cannot be ſo exquiſite in his skill therein, as he that hath ſerved to it any conſiderable time. The application is eaſie. And what although (as you ſay) they were no Lawyers, ſo they be juſt; nor Divines, if pious? Yet let us not imagine they are the leſs theſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are good Souldiers: ſhould we think Armies want Reaſon, becauſe they have Strength? I, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, think that the knowing of their ſtrength addes to their Reaſon. Why may not a woman be fair, though ſhe be chaſte? yea truely I think her Chaſtity makes her the fairer: if plurality of good qualities were not compatible in one perſon, the concatenation of Vertues would not be a ſo generally received opinion amongſt the Wiſe: as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſometimes are eſteemed bold, even when they do but ſpeak; ſo may Souldiers be called prudent, whilſt they are in fighting.</p>
            <p>A well-grounded power nevertheleſs is that which gives the eſſential being to Authority, and the Sword that which infallibly governs every where both in <hi>Monarchies</hi> and <hi>States.</hi> Is not the Man accounted the Head in Matrimony, becauſe of his being more powerful and vigorous then the woman? <hi>Genoa</hi> choſe <hi>Spain</hi> for her Protector, becauſe of his Power; and <hi>Geneva</hi> the French King, not for his great Wit, as I conceive it: therefore is it that we ſhould have a more intrinſecal relation to our immediate Governours, and more intime application of our Obedience to their Commands.</p>
            <p>This I ſay not to juſtifie every Conqueſt, although the Scriptures ordain us to be pliable to all ſuperiour powers, becauſe power is from God; of which paſſage I refer the interpretation to Divines, and in the interim aver the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115250:6"/>of the <hi>Turks</hi> Authority, albeit it be ſeconded with ſufficient Power; becauſe the Queſtion is not ſo much of Power alone, as of Power with Goodneſs, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitancie of Moral Vertues; whereof there is ſuch ſtore in my <hi>Lord General</hi> and his Officers, that in the Legend of all the <hi>Worthies</hi> have not been read more glorious atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with leſs oſtentation, nor more ſelf-denyal in ſuch actions as in former Ages have been honoured with the ſublimeſt triumphs.</p>
            <p>I, but (ſay you) the Parliament choſe the <hi>General.</hi> What then? Although I have already proved the contrary; Is not the King of <hi>Poland</hi> above the People that elected him? And beſides, it is not the <hi>Parliament</hi> which by his Officers was diſſolved, that made him <hi>General;</hi> the Army had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, and new-molded it ſeveral times before; and, which is more, if this late Parliamentary Authority was derived from the people, and that the Peoples ſafety, which is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Supreme Law,</hi> conſiſt in the welfare of the Army, Is not the Army by that means protector of both, and the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers thereof the fitteſt Legiſlators when any danger is imminent? It is then upon that neceſſity (as many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it) of the preſervation of the Peoples ſafety, which was thought to be in very great hazard, by the too-long ſitting at the Helm of men of private ſpirits, minding one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their own buſineſſes, that my <hi>Lord General</hi> and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers did re-aſſume that power which properly was theirs. Or rather, to expreſs it more warily, as the Lord of hoſts ſtirred up the <hi>Parliament</hi> to new-model the <hi>Army,</hi> for the better furtherance of the War: ſo hath the God of peace moved the <hi>Army,</hi> by way of retaliation, to new-model the Government, for the greater tranquillity of the People.</p>
            <p>Had it not been for the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> Treaty (I believe) with the <hi>late King</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> had, by eſtabliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115250:7"/>him in his throne, hindred the erection of this Common-wealth; as being perhaps ſenſible, that the ſtream of a <hi>Parliament</hi> can have no longer infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence with any ſhew of right over the people, after the drying up of the Regal ſource from whence it ſprang at firſt. It is that Army then, which by expulſing the old government, is become the true baſis of the new one, and by deſtroying <hi>Monarchy</hi> hath ſet up that fabrick of a State, the managing whereof lyes upon their ſhoulders. Who burneth the wood en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendreth the flame, which domineers over all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible ſtuff it can lay hold on: whilſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſate, it was the <hi>Army</hi> did animate them, the <hi>Army</hi> was their ſoul, and the Maſter-wheel by which they moved, in which ſenſe I think my Lord <hi>General</hi> did acknowledge the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> ſoveraginty, and in ſo doing did derogate nothing from himſelf and the Officers, who virtually governed by them, and thus in my opinion are to be interpreted all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of mentioning the Supreme Authority of this Nation, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of which authority the Officers of the Army were the very Soul, and they but the outward Organs Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſmically Repreſentative of the great body of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick.</p>
            <p>In your letter you attribute the brains to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to the Army nothing but hands; but I ſay it is more like the brains were in the Officers, or at leaſt more brains, allowing ſtill the hands and feet to the Common Souldiery: it is not the brains of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that have a proper influence upon the body of an <hi>Army,</hi> for the brains readily admit not of ſo great a ſeparation and diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the hands; reſolution and prudence ſhould be ſtill coupled together, elſe the body politick cannot long eſcape from ruine: timorouſneſs in counſel maketh men
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115250:7"/>forbear the doing of good, and too much temerity in the practical part prompteth hot ſpirits to the committing of wickedneſs, but together joyned, they make a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent temper; for from uniting the vehement heat of the one, to the extream coldneſs of the other, there reſulteth a remiſſer quality in its mediocrity comfortable; this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording certainty in direction, and that a celerity in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of what is good.</p>
            <p>Whereas there is a buzzing, that the only refuge of the People was in former times the Parliament: ſo may I ſay that the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their ſtinging afflictions had the like recourſe to the Brazen Serpent, which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs was afterwards very lawfully taken down: we ought not to be ſuch nominal Stateſmen as to dote upon the words of <hi>Parliament, Law, Priviledges,</hi> or I cannot tell what, whilſt all the things ſignified by them are violated and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed even by thoſe that idolize them in outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: this is but like the doing of miſchief <hi>in nomine domini,</hi> and wrapping a Wolf in a Lambs skin. What is the matter of words, or how the Supreme Authority be called, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the country be well governed? Would not any coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man that is hungry, be better pleaſed, to have a loaſ of bread preſented to him, although you call it a ſtone, then a ſtone to break his faſt upon, which you ſhall call a loaf? What elſe is a <hi>Parliament,</hi> a ſacred aſſembly, the repreſentatives of all the people? unleſs their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings be accordingly very conſcionable, and juſt, they are aſſuredly but words of no greater veneration then of old were <hi>Tyranny, Kingſhip,</hi> and <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> which in <hi>Greece, Rome,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> where they were moſt honoured, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came afterwards odious: after the ſame manner, though this late Parliament was called the peoples Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, and that the whole Nation did own them for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115250:8"/>ſuch, yet do the people in general ſeem to be very well pleaſed with their diſſolution, and not only they, but the ſoundeſt part alſo of themſelves, as is perceivable by the facility wherewith ſo great an action was performed; it being done without any noiſe, ſtruggle, or yet diſcontent but of very few.</p>
            <p>But how comes that (ſay you) to be juſt now, which formerly in the late <hi>Kings</hi> coming to the Houſe, but to require the number only of five members, was accounted unjuſt, and a ground ſufficient for making a defenſive war? I anſwer, The caſe is quite other; for beſides that then was a time, wherein formalities were a great deal more to be regarded, Martial Law, and Military atchievements being things in this Land at that time quite unknown, the late King by his thus forcible coming in unto the Houſe did break the priviledges which both his predeceſſors &amp; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had given, and therefore having reſigned his power to that <hi>Parliament,</hi> by vertue whereof they then ſate legally, he ought, if there were any refractary members, to have conſulted with the remainder of the body concerning them, who together with the reſt of the houſe had by him that placed them undoubtedly been raiſed, had not they been taken into the tuition and patrociny of the Army, whoſe Power being from God, he hath accordingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued unbroken amidſt the revolution of various and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable dangers, to the aſtoniſhment not only of this Iſland, but of the whole world beſides.</p>
            <p>You ſay the action was violent: I ſay, No; for it was carried on with the greateſt modeſtie and diſcretion that could be imagined. As for that which is called the rupture of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> it was as nothing: for if the action in it ſelf was juſt (as I affirm it was) officious lingring cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, in ſuch important matters as can admit of no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115250:8"/>delays, are not to be regarded: Formalities, at beſt, in ſuch a juncture of occaſions, are but imbelliſhing orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or as paintings upon Sepulchres, where there is any tottenneſs in the main intendments covered by them. A Cordial in a Pitcher is more eſtimable then Poyſon in an Agat; and a Homely Friend better worth the accoſting, then a Courtly Enemy. He that permits one to wear his Cloak for a while, expecting he will do it civilly, may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards require it from him, when he ſees him abuſe it. If thoſe of the Houſe be collationed with the Officers of the Army, we ſhall finde that Parliaments are compoſed but of Country ſpirits for the moſt part, not much inclined to Milice, and who, though an humor of enriching themſelvs ſhould impoveriſh the Country, will be ſo much the longer before they can goodly be made ſenſible of it, that ſuchlike men as they being but very little or ſeldom acquainted with dangers and loſſes, are never much nor often touched with a compaſſion or fellow-feeling of the ſufferings of others: and any man will acknowledge himſelf more obliged to him or them that freely hazard their lives for him, then to ſuch as will but faintly grant his Petition after a twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>months delay perhaps, and expending more in attendance (to ſpeak of nothing elſe) then he gets by it.</p>
            <p>Admit there be better Lawyers, and greater Scholars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> then any in the Roll of the <hi>Army</hi>-Officers; yet will it make nothing for your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for that ſuch skilful men ought rather to be ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to the Officers, then thereby to pretend any Maſtery over them, is by this apparent, that Speculation aſcends un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Action, wherein conſiſts the life of all buſineſs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, thoſe Literate men ſhould very humbly and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately ſubmit their ſtudious elucubrations to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute diſpoſure of theſe other worthy Patriots, who by a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115250:9"/>Practical induſtry make the Theory of the former uſeful to the furtherance of the benefit of this Commonwealth. Should not Law be ſubordinate to Equity; and Learning to Goodneſs? God hath revealed more to Good men then to Scholars; and we finde not anywhere, that either Divines or Lawyers are men of better lives then others. Take along with you the tract of all the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and you ſhall ſee that they were but obſcure men both in Law &amp; Literature: yea, their very Kings were taken and ſelected out of Shepherds, to ſignifie unto us that Law depends not altogether upon Learning: our Mindes are able to judge of Good and Bad, as our Eyes of Colours, although many times ſelf-intereſt diſtracteth the thoughts of theſe our mindes, and quite diverteth them from the true and right apprehenſion of the object; as the Jaundiſe maketh every Colour appear yellow to the eye, which without that imperfection would have diſcerned aright of any thing expoſed to the ſight thereof.</p>
            <p>In my opinion, therefore, the Supreme power ought nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be in Lawyers, nor Divines, nor both; becauſe thoſe that have been enriched by private contentions, will never harbour in their breſts ſuch publike ſpirits as ſhall ſuffice to eſtabliſh domeſtick ſafety, and gain ſtand forraign inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: for he is to be accounted the beſt ſervant, that doth his maſters will, and not that other who ſays this is my maſters will, yet doth but his own. Thoſe quaint expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and flouriſhes of Rhetorick which in gilding a bad cauſe, being the effects of depraved Learning, do but caſt a thick miſt over the eyes of the hearers underſtandings, and fill their abuſed ears with empty ſounds of new No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, are not to be expected from the Officers of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> who, delivering their minds ingenuouſly without either fard or affectation, proſecute good ends above-boord, by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115250:9"/>means void of all diſſimulation and deceitfulneſs.</p>
            <p>Here will I not utter ſo much as one ſyllable either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>the whole Body</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or any of its <hi>members,</hi> in taxing them with unneceſſary delays of granting the ſubjects juſt demands, their having intended and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly proſecuted their own affairs more then thoſe of the Publike, and ſuch-like, whereof there is a great deal alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy publiſhed by others; becauſe I will not offer to do the Souldiery ſo much wrong, as to juſtifie their actions by the indirect way of Recriminating others: I ſhall remain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with this comparative expreſſion, in ſaying, That thoſe who no leſs freely expoſe their perſons for the defence of their Country, and maintenance of the Liberties thereof, into ſuch extreme perils, as if they had the ſhift of a new life, wherewith to cloath themſelves the next day (life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more precious then external goods) ſhould be preferred to thoſe that for their own enrichment (if any ſuch there be) would do the meaneſt prejudice to the livelihood of another.</p>
            <p>The action (ſay you) is raſh, unlawful, and ſtrange. I think it truly more ſtrange, that any ſuch expreſſion ſhould proceed from a rational man: for as for the good of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, water ſometimes mounteth, and air deſcends, quite contrary to the propenſion of their own natures; ſo is it that what many times hath been found unlawful in private actions, may in publike ones be eſteemed very juſt. Had <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtood upon his principles of ſubjection &amp; obedience to the Laws of the Prince of his native Country, (which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs the <hi>Army</hi> was not ſo much liable unto in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Parliament</hi>) what had become of the Liberty of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and enlargement of the houſe of <hi>Jacob?</hi> However, although at the firſt appearance it ſeem to be an act of Will, yet is it ſo far from being unreaſonable, that it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115250:10"/>is the laſt act and reſult of the higheſt pitch of Reaſon, and more praiſe-worthy then that action of the hands, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is brought a wholeſome Potion to purge the brain for the ſafety of the whole body. If the Reaſons have not as yet been made known, it is becauſe of thoſe worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's being employed about matters of greater moment; theirs being the practical, &amp; ſo fitter for Government, and that of others but Speculative, which grounded meerly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an aerial diſcourſe of Laws, of <hi>aquum,</hi> of <hi>bonum,</hi> or other ſuch-like ſpecious things, proving, for the moſt part, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther always, in ſuch ſpirits as are not bent on action, but common and general notions, do never produce any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable thing; which defect is not to be found in my <hi>Lord General,</hi> nor the Officers of his <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay they are not ſo literate as thoſe of the <hi>Parliament:</hi> I ſay, For any thing you know they are; but albeit they were not, it is not much matter, ſo they be poſitively good, and comparatively better then ſuch as are more learned; which I truſt they are: for with ſo much knowledge as is fitting they are endowed; and in ſtead of ſuperfluous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Literature, they make a ſerious application of the skill they have (wherewith they are qualified in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent meaſure) to the perfect accompliſhment of the moſt commendable actions. It is not he who makes the beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Vertue, that is therefore the moſt vertuous man. The beſt Divines are not the godlyeſt perſons, nor were there any Lawyers in the Golden age. Subtilty in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, trivial quirks, and curious reſearches, in ſub-diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing of abſtracted flimflam-notions, help very much to cry up men to the title of good Scholars, in the eſtimation of frothy Wits.</p>
            <p>That we have men powerful, and ſuch as are good, to rule over us, is all we ſhould deſire: and if by misfortune
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115250:10"/>we were neceſſitated to make election of one alone of thoſe qualities, it were better (in my opinion) our Governours were deſtitute of goodneſs, then that they lacked power: for good men, without power, would but leave us to the ſpoil of every body, whoſe wickedneſs they are not able to ſuppreſs, and abandon us as ſtubble before the fire, to thoſe would bring us to a ſudden &amp; utter deſolation: but ſo they have power, although otherwiſe they be bad enough, they will in all probability protect us againſt both forraign and domeſtick Invaſions, were it to no other end, but to prey upon us themſelves; which nevertheleſs they will be loth to do with too great extremity, becauſe by thoſe means not being able to do it long, they would by injuring others but weaken themſelves, and ſo at laſt abſtain from it out of the meer motive of ſelf-love. If Power be thus much to be preferred, when it goeth fingle, which I ſpeak in favour of the Souldiery, Why then ſhould not the Officers of the <hi>Army</hi> have their due pre-eminence above any other, ſeeing beſides the ſacred power that is in their hands, they are the greateſt paterns of Piety, and examples of Goodneſs, that the world affordeth?</p>
            <p>It is abſolute and uncontrollable (ſay you) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dangerous: I anſwer you, If an abſolute power muſt reſt ſomewhere in every government (according to the doctrine of the beſt politicians) it can (in my opinion) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in no more convenient place then its own Sphere. What earthquakes happen, and violent concuſſion of things of great weight, even by what (to our ſeeming) is of far leſs moment, when they are debarred the liberty of working about their own center, as air or fire incloſed when either of them appetes an expanſion!</p>
            <p>Though other States now adayes be not governed ſo, what then? all States are not governed after one way, nor
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115250:11"/>Monarchies neither; becauſe the different inclinations of thoſe that have the power, make what is unjuſt in one place to be accounted elſewhere juſt, and yet poſſibly there may be latitude enough for juſtice in both. Was not the body of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> an Army, led under the conduct of their General <hi>Moſes?</hi> who albeit he admitted of elders to eaſe him of a burthen, yet did not any acknowledge the Supreme Authority to lye in them. Would you in <hi>Scotland</hi> be like the <hi>Iews</hi> in their convenanting, and yet diſagree from them in that wherein did conſiſt their greateſt honor? There is in <hi>Scotland</hi> (as I conceive it) no other kind of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive but Cavalier or Presbyterian; and ſeeing this latter one thruſt out the maſter of that other, theſe others will (in my opinion) be content to be ruled by thoſe that did protect them againſt the Malignancy of their competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: if the other party be not pleaſed with it, I muſt think certainly, that it is upon a ground more deſtructive to that country, ſuch as to have the Miniſtery to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter it, and all the people implicitely tyed to have their dark faiths pin'd on thoſe mens black ſleeves, although moſt of them, for covetouſneſs, cruelty, and oppreſſion, be equal to the moſt corrupt of the laity.</p>
            <p>You are afraid that by this change <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall be more in ſlaved then ever. I muſt confeſs it hath not that ſhew of liberty, which it had in the dayes of <hi>Malcolm Kianmore;</hi> but taking it in general (ſome few perſons only excepted that ſqueezed the reſt) the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage was hardly greater then that which it endured under Presbytery, whoſe yoak in that Nation becoming lighter, as the power of the Engliſh increaſed therein (though not altogether taken off; becauſe of the ſuppoſed prevalency, which ſome of the Presbyterially-affected Members of the late diſſolved Houſe, had over the counſels of the prime rulers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115250:11"/>there) you have now juſt reaſon to thank God, that by this change you are like to be relieved out of the jaws of ſo wild a monſter, and freed from that <hi>Knoxian</hi> ſlavery, which made you miſerable within your ſelves, and deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto all the other Nations of the World. Nor need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any of you to grudge at his being conſtrained (when it ſhall ſo happen) to ſubmit no longer to the ſupreme diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Kirk; ſeeing the taking of ſuch a coercive courſe is to uſe no more violence, then when one is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from proſecuting his own ruine, and yet (I think) the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> is not able to provide you with Governours that ſhall be more tender in laying of burthens upon your conſciences, then my Lord <hi>General,</hi> and thoſe ſelect Officers of his <hi>Army,</hi> under whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you are, who are all of them haters of contentious divinity, and the forcing of mens minds to embrace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known opinions; and who having done ſo great matters both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> will be now (I hope) very careful not to eclipſe their reputation by miſuſing <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although there ſhould be found in it ſome diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pancy in matters of faith from the upright and true one; yet ſo long as thoſe opinions break not out into action, and do onely hover about things concerning another world, there is no doubt but that they will acknowledge, how without the help of man, or any need of his coacting power, God hath a way of his own for the reclaiming of ſuch: this ſtraine to any judicious man will ſeem more moderate then that of the Presbyter, whoſe ambition it was to have the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Covenant tread underfoot all the other profeſſions in the world.</p>
            <p>Tell me, I pray you, were not all of you (and that not long ago) epidemically infected with the deaſe of believing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115250:12"/>that in the yeer of the laſt <hi>Iubilee,</hi> the ſaid covenant ſhould be pompouſly ſet up in <hi>Saint Peters</hi> Church at <hi>Rome?</hi> nay further, was there any thing more commonly preached amongſt you, then the curſing of <hi>Meroz</hi> for not coming out to help the Lord againſt the mighty? which text they applyed both for and againſt Monarchy, whilſt the enemy remained ſtill one and the ſame, ſo cunning they were in making a noſe of wax of the Scriptures: as likewiſe the curſing of thoſe that did the work of the Lord negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and withheld their hand from blood. After this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they ſtirred up (you know) the people there to be active in going about the deſigne of making an univerſal Kirk, which if they would do, promiſes were made to them, of being Gods ſelect and covenanted people, of the driving of the Nations before them, and their eating the fat and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſweet: all which had events ſo ſuitable to my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, though contrary to their predictions, that now there is no more common ſaying, then that your Miniſters have been falſe Prophets from the beginning, and men of doctrines inconſiſtent with any ſecular govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being ſo much the more dangerous, that they did always ſpeak of God, and accounted their cauſe to be his.</p>
            <p>For had they been contented to have ſaid in their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, Gentlemen, I am to tell you a ſtory, and a tale truly worthy your hearing, although it might have been thought a kind of irreligious expreſſion in a place of ſuch reverence; yet would it have been of leſs prejudice to the auditory, and impiety in the ſpeaker, then to have expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves after this faſhion, Thus ſaith God, this is the meaning of his covenant, even when what they ſpoke was upon contrivances of their own; for the promoval of by ends deſtructive to many duties which God requireth of us.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115250:12"/>
            <p>Such as were not Presbyterians, they aſperſed with the name of <hi>Papiſt;</hi> and would have continued ſtill ſo, if Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence had not put the power in the hands of thoſe, who, though better Proteſtants then they, do nevertheleſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Papal authority to be leſs tyrannical then theirs, the effects whereof are ſo pernicious, that it were better for you in that Country to be left to your ſelvs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Government at all, the meer common laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in ſuch a caſe of Anarchy, being able to retain you in thoſe duties, which, being drunken with the dregs of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Hierarchical Soveraignty (whether in one or many) you would otherwiſe be enforced to violate.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many other ſuch reaſons (which any thing amply to deduce would require a Treatiſe apart) do give ſufficient evidence againſt Eccleſiaſtical ſupremacie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we ſtand in no great need; ſeeing all divine Laws are naturally imprinted in the heart of every good man. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs expelled the Papiſts from amongſt you, Pride overthrew the Biſhops, &amp; Lying, with both theſe, is like to pull down your Miniſters; neither of all which qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whether joyntly or ſeverally, are any way beſeeming men of a Legiſlative Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Your Presbyterian Tenets, like <hi>Scyrrus</hi> and <hi>Procruſtes</hi> beds (to which long men were equalled by curtaling, and the ſhort by racking out their limbs) will have all manner of Conſciences ſo adapted to them, as to make the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hearts ſhed innocent blood, and bring the proudeſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates to ſubmit to their <hi>Maſ-Johns Delphian</hi> Oracle, who poſſibly pretending to a Prophetical ſpirit, leaveth almoſt no place untouched with his <hi>entouſiaſtick</hi> bolts, but that wherein is fixed the blank of Truth, which he maketh ſhew to level at. Thus, without conſidering the various tempers of mindes, they would befool all men alike, and take the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115250:13"/>ſame courſe with the higheſt ſpirits, which <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> did with the Commons of <hi>Rome,</hi> by means of his Nymph <hi>Agyria:</hi> or <hi>Sertorius</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> by his white Hinde with the inhabitants there, &amp; ſo poſſeſs men with conceits of their infallibilities in the diſpenſations of providence, even when they ſay no more, but, <hi>This will come to paſs, for ſo God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed it: Presbytery muſt rule, for it is according to the Word;</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more eaſie to ſay any thing, then to give a good reaſon for it: for, to ſpeak truely, they never bring any reaſon but Teſtimony, and that onely grounded upon their own bare interpretations, flowing from worldly reſpects, ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, and private deſignes towards dignity, profit, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which for many yeers together hath run ſo impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in that country, to the ſtirring up of choler and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation in the auditory, againſt thoſe at whoſe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or inclinations they had any diſlike, that, as a clown who hath long faſted, will with a little ſtrong drink be quickly fudled, thoſe incendiary Churchmen do juſt ſo work upon the ſpirits of ſuch as by a long abſtinence from any nouriſhing doctrine are with their hot-waters of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion apt to be inebriated; there being no more ſeveral kinds of ſtrong liquour, then there is variety of operating up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch addle-brained heads.</p>
            <p>There is hardly any judicious man but knoweth, that it was neither learning, piety, nor patriotiſm that perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any of that Nation to Presbytery, nor had they any of thoſe three qualities in them that were the perſwaders; yet let us not think it ſtrange: for, as a cup of good Sack will make one fight, where Reaſon cannot prompt him to it, when he is ſober; ſo will the vapouring words of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery preachers oftentimes intoxicate a giddy-headed popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſs, when ſound and ſolid inſtructions are able to make no impreſſion.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115250:13"/>
            <p>But that all <hi>Scotland,</hi> comprehending all the degrees of its inhabitants, ſhould have been brought under that yoak, is (in my opinion) the onely miracle that was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Presbytery, and one (I think) never a whit leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then any mentioned in the <hi>Romiſh Legend,</hi> had that people of late been endowed with ſpirits equal to thoſe of their predeceſſors. This degenerate deviation hath made moſt of the Nations of Chriſtendom (if not all) look aſquint upon them.</p>
            <p>When the Presbyterians of <hi>Scotland</hi> prevailed againſt the King's party, they intituled themſelves <hi>The people of God,</hi> becauſe of their victories; which appellation, for ſuch a reaſon, is every whit as due to the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> by having ſubjugated to his Scepter all the Chriſtians of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Armenia.</hi> They likewiſe prove in <hi>Scotland</hi> the ſame concluſion by their being afflicted; which title (ſhould it require no other cauſe) might as properly have been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the <hi>Canaanites</hi> and <hi>Gibeonites.</hi> After ſuch a manner of reaſoning, we may infer all things to be precious and ſweet, that are of the colour of Gold and Honey: we may very well know, that affirmatively to attribute one general thing to two, makes not therefore thoſe two things to be one.</p>
            <p>In a word, if that their ſeeming wiſdom in Divinity had bin turned to a more real performance of goodnes towards one another, they would have gained more Proſelytes. I would not here have any man to think, that in twitting thoſe men, I ſpeak againſt Learning, but plainly aſſever that the Divines, both Epiſcopal and Presbyterian, by curbing mens Fancies, and ſuffering nothing to paſs the Preſs which did not like them, buryed much Learning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the aſhes of their ſullenneſs, which ſince their fall hath begun to break forth into flaſhes of a moſt comfortable
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115250:14"/>flame and chearful light. Of Presbytery at this time will I not ſpeak much more, becauſe to rip it up to the full would require a Volume by it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Another part of your Letter ſeemeth to import, that you do not hold your ſelves under this Government ſo altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther free as formerly you were. What is (I pray you) the freedom you had under the Presbyter? was there any but ſuch as ſhored up <hi>their</hi> intereſts, that could ſay he had a propriety to his own goods? was there ever any thing more common amongſt the Kirk-men there, then to preach men out of their eſtates, which no other Proteſtants of this Iſle did offer to do, but they? By which tyrannie of theirs, and other preſſures proceeding from them, the moſt part of the inhabitants of that Land were ſo heavily oppreſſed, that laying aſide thoſe that are ſequeſtred, whereof there are not many, the remanent of the Country is now under a far more eaſie yoak then it was at any time theſe nine yeers paſt: for although the Seſs in <hi>Scotland</hi> be ſix times greater then in <hi>England,</hi> and truely more then that poor Country can well bear; yet is it much leſs then it was under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Presbytery: for I have known Gentlemen there, whoſe whole rents were taken up to the payment of Publike dues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſticks (I know) in your ſtomacks, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould be your Maſters: yet to be united with <hi>England,</hi> and to be accounted as one Nation, I believe you would not think diſhonourable. The territories of theſe two domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons God hath joyned and united; and truly I think that in former Ages it was the devil did diſunite their hearts; of which diviſion the <hi>Frenches</hi> taking advantage, ſtruck in with the <hi>Scots:</hi> but what gain was it to <hi>Scotland</hi> to have their brothers in <hi>England</hi> their enemies? or did your joyning with <hi>France</hi> enrich <hi>Scotland?</hi> Did it make your Traffick to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115250:14"/>flouriſh, or put your Gentlemen into any happie ſtate? or rather, did not your falling out with <hi>England</hi> put you into a quite contrary condition, and made you ſuch, that you had almoſt hardly any thing elſe to brag of, but an ancient poverty, and invincible hatred againſt your brothers?</p>
            <p>I know your common regret and condolement is, that <hi>Scotland</hi> was never ſo before as it is now, it having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed a longer Series of Kings, without interruption of a Conqueſt, then any other kingdome in <hi>Europe,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their ſubdument was attempted by the <hi>Romanes, Picts, Danes, Saxons,</hi> and others, ſome whereof went tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row with their deſignes in this your neighbour-nation of <hi>England.</hi> What then? though <hi>England</hi> hath had more change of Governours, ſo have fair women of ſuiters, even unto proſtitution: and therefore, if beſides the valour and prudence of the natives, any thing elſe, ſuch as hills, bogs, heath, hunger, cold, or ſuch-like, proceeding from the inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſibility and poverty of the Country, hath kept you till now a Virgin-nation, unexpoſed to the embraces of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Conquerour, you have nothing there to boaſt of more then others, whoſe valour being equal with yours, hath been oftner broke, for the want of theſe rugged aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances which do conſtantly attend you; a reſiſtance made from an intrinſecal vertue, being much more commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then a non-admittance becauſe of outward impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: as a chaſte woman at a Royal Court, is more praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy then an encloyſtred Nun.</p>
            <p>To be a free Nation, is to be ſubject to reaſonable men: for, to conquer our own paſſions, and ſubmit our ſelves to a juſt power, is the greateſt freedom of any. To be left at random without Governours; to be in a continual ſtate of war with your neighbours; or, like <hi>Cannibals,</hi> to be ſtill devouring one another, without fear of Law, or terrour of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115250:15"/>puniſhment, is not to enjoy the liberty of a free Nation; for that permiſſion to do wickedly, cannot be accounted li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in a humane ſociety; nor is the freedom of ſuch of the <hi>Weſt-Indian</hi> Savages as remain unconquered, any great honour to them. After the <hi>Romane</hi> conqueſt of <hi>Greece,</hi> (which nevertheleſs was accounted (and that deſervedly) a very warlike Nation) the <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Lacedmonians,</hi> who before that time did conſtantly war againſt one another, lived then together in a very peaceable tranquillity, and were not aſhamed of their ſubjection to the <hi>Romane</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. What <hi>feuds</hi> have you had in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the utter undoing of ſeveral great Families, even when you did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute your ſelves as free a people as any in the world? If now you would attain to the renown of being an honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Nation, ſtrive with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by way of emulation, who ſhall love other beſt, who ſhall ſhew moſt valour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a forraign invader, who ſhall be moſt judicious in Counſel, who ſhall give greateſt encouragement to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and Merchandiſe it with moſt dexterity. You would have thought it a moſt glorious thing to have conquered <hi>England,</hi> although but to have done that in matter of the union of both Nations, which king <hi>James,</hi> for all his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much-cried-up wiſdom, could not get effectuated. What although the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have conquered the beſt part of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> if they have the ſame end before their eyes, which you would have had? Nor can I imagine, ſo that you joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become one Nation, that there is any greater matter in it, whether the <hi>Engliſh</hi> or you have been moſt inſtrumental in the means whereby that great work is accompliſhed, then whether with the right or left hand we ſhall eat, ſo the meat be good, and that we digeſt it well.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Picts</hi> have been amongſt you, and you expelled them: ſo were the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Saxons,</hi> and you likewiſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115250:15"/>overthrew them: the <hi>Romans</hi> have been there alſo, and you embraced their language: nor do I think it is for nought that you have theſe many ages paſt ſpoke the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue: they are now come to dwell amongſt you, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you as well with their vertues, as with the dialect of their ſpeech; and if they do it in ſomwhat more then equal terms, do not you nevertheleſs offer to repine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at; the <hi>Sabins</hi> were in a better condition then ever, after their conjunction with the <hi>Romans,</hi> although the <hi>Sabins</hi> were the more ancient people, and that the <hi>Roman</hi> name ſwallowed up the glory of the other. You ſhould not flatter your ſelves with fond conceits, and thereby incur the danger of loſing the ſubſtance for the ſhadow; for to be ſuch a Free-Nation as to be civil with authority above others, is a thing rather to be wiſht for then expected by you: the ſoveraigne of the Planets hath removed his beams the further from you, and <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptune</hi> fettered you with his watry ſhekels, that you may not harbour in your mind ſuch ambitious thoughts: it is much if the whole Iſle unanimouſly joyned, perform ſuch magnanimous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements.</p>
            <p>Now for your further information in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, I have thought it not unexpedient to ſend you with this Letter, another of that worthy gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>N.</hi> LL. written to a gentleman in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try touching the diſſolution of the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the reaſons thereof; wherein is ſhown you, how providence, many times, by ſeveral inviſible degrees, brings forth her propoſed intendments with thoſe inſtruments, which ſeem to do the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115250:16"/>contrary; how many of the <hi>Parliament</hi>-men were content to ſelf-center, and lay little deſignes for their own greatneſs, as if they had been called to the houſe to make up private breaches, and not publike ones: how private intereſts were carryed on by way of exchange: how incredibly long their delayes were in granting of the moſt juſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions: how they did ſpin out the time in the toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a feather even whilſt they ſuffered the weightieſt mattes of any to ſink: how unjuſt they were in the courſes taken for paying of Souldiers Debenters, and in their emitting of Surveyors for overvaluing and undervaluing of lands to their own private advantage, and palpable prejudice to the Commonwealth; and how by ſuch means men of inconſiderable fortunes before they were mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berfied, had afterwards raiſed themſelves to huge and vaſt eſtates.</p>
            <p>He ſhews us alſo in in the ſame Letter, how God hath ſingularly owned my <hi>Lord</hi> GENERAL and his ARMY, in crowning them by very remarkable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and how without the <hi>Army</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> had been expoſed to the affronts of the multitude, as when by the Apprentices they were ſhut up within doors: he tells us how the liberty of the people being recovered by the ſword, the Army
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115250:16"/>ought to be the <hi>ſuperviſor</hi> of thoſe liberties, that no incroachment be permitted to be made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: and that he who hath power to command, hath alſo power to guide, the one without the other being inſignificant: he expreſſeth likewiſe, how the formerly-mentioned defects and abuſes were to be redreſſed and remedied either by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> People, or Army: the firſt were ſo cunning they would not; the ſecond ſo unskilful that they could not; and that therefore it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent to the third like wiſe guardians to do it: and thus as arbitrators taking into their moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration the ſafety of the people, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of themſelves were a part, after they had percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that neither addreſſes, reaſons, propoſals, nor petitions could prevaile any thing, they were forced to have recourſe to that of the Phyſician <hi>ure &amp; ſeca:</hi> furthermore he ſhews, to the end we ſtartle not at the change of the Supream Authority from the name of Parliament to that of Counſel, that it is of as little effect, and ſignifieth no more then if a King or State ſhould make ſome alteration in the titles of their credentials: being pleaſed hereto to ſubjoyn this Queſtion, Whether it be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be in ſlavery under the name of Liberty, or in liberty under the effects of ſlavery. All which, with many more, you in the ſaid letter may peruſe at leiſure, without omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that paſſage of his where he ſayeth, that the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian is a Jeſuite in a <hi>Geneva</hi>-cloak, onely ſome what more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115250:17"/>
            <p>Here without <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> or any other language then plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> have I delivered my mind unto you, and that barely, without ſearching ſo much as one teſtimony, or cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any place in either ſacred or humane writings; for that the truth ſeeks neither corners, nor embelliſhments; and that it is true which I have written; it is my firme opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, in which I intend to continue, till with ſtronger argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I be convinced, then as yet I have mentioned, or ſhall be able to produce, in aſſerting my <hi>Lord Generals</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and vindication of his Excellency and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Councel of Officers.</p>
            <p>Theſe things (I hope) you will take in the better part, that they have proceeded from me who you know was never nor am a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> who am not, nor ever will be a <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian:</hi> and who affects no <hi>Sectarianiſm;</hi> but loves to be ſuch a ſincere profeſſors of the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as to lay hold on faith in him, and accordingly regulate the whole courſe of my life thereby: and who beſides thoſe adjuncts will not decline this other one, that I am a compatriot of yours, and ſuch a one (which I ſpeak without either flattery or ſelf-love) as hath ever from his yeers of diſcretion upwards, ſtudyed the promoval of the honour of his native country, and proſecuted it to the outmoſt of his endeavours.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>This Tuſday the 17. <hi>May</hi> 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your humble ſervant</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="text">
            <p>
               <hi>In the title Page, next line but one before the imprinted, for</hi> added <hi>read</hi> premiſed. <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 21. <hi>Read</hi> Prolixity whereof. <hi>page</hi> 2. <hi>lin.</hi> 25. <hi>read</hi> all which,</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
